[Music]
all right hello welcome everyone
this is the actin flap quarterly round
table number 20.
number two in 2022
it's june 29th
so welcome to the active inference lab
we're a participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links on this slide
this is recorded in an archive live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
today it's a quarterly roundtable lab
meeting
so we're going to have a lot of updates
to share
on some of the activities of the second
quarter of 2022 and also share a lot of
next steps at the project and at the
organizational scale
so let's begin with an introduction
slash warm-up
we can say hello
and
maybe as if it were a paper we were
discussing what was just one memory or
something
that you learned this quarter or some
participation that you just want to
call out and highlight
so
i'll go
first i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and
have a lot to add but just
saw so much amazing participation
and development
this quarter um like without
having compiled these slides with
everybody
so much would have just
um
it all happened so fast
and so looking forward to catching up on
this and also building structures so
that we can even
have more clarity internally and
externally about what we're working on
like there's just quite a contrast with
hopefully this lab meeting and even our
previous five or six
and i'll pass it to blue
yeah this quarter was awesome i think
the launch of the textbook group has
been like pretty mind-blowing for me um
that's like a new uh
thing that we've done and um
yeah i am enjoying it and looking
forward to future cohorts and part two
of the textbook group but that to me was
kind of um like like a pivotal a pivotal
moment in this last
three months
uh and i'll pass it to jakob
so hi i'm markup i'm a student in the uk
and
the textbook group
was
also
the highlight uh
from
this quarter for me um
and i
one thing that
i learned probably would have to be uh
that multi-agent active inference is
a lot more
interesting and harder than
initially meets the eye
and i'll pass it to alex
yeah thanks
i'm alex and i can agree that
education as a survivor from the lab is
the most important
thing
for this quarter
so for study group
as well as for our farmers what we are
planning and
now preparing for participants and more
broader community
is
the most important thing from our
deposit to iran
thank you alex
my name is ivan i'm
in romania i'm a researcher in systems
management school
last quarter we
with our team done a lot of work uh
in case of
education
as well as
in case of administration
in a lap in the lab
level so i'm looking forward to
development for all the directions we
are
we are going to
all right let's get into
the projects
so first we're going to
provide some updates on the project
scale so these are things that happen
during second quarter for a variety of
projects
all right first as
mentioned by several of us here
we began the first cohort of the active
inference textbook group in may 2022
and that'll go through july 2022
and we are working on the first five
chapters of this active inference
textbook by
thomas parr giovanni pizzulo and carl
fristen and just to give a little taste
though there's a few other pieces too
that people who participate in future
cohorts will get to experience
um there's a collaborative questions and
discourse
affordance which has allowed people to
introduce basic clarifying questions as
well as questions about application and
about
philosophy all different kinds of
questions have been addressed in a way
that really clearly references which
part of the text it's about which page
or which figure and in fact all the
tables figures equations and so on have
been annotated using coda such that by
just clicking on it you can see a pop-up
of a figure and that allows a very
interactive way of dealing with
different terms and different
objects of attention
and then on the right
we have some of the work by those
engaged most in the math learning
where for each equation
we are aiming to have a natural language
description
first just reading out the equation as
it is and also here
active inference ontology terms are in
blue
so this will facilitate the translation
of equations across human languages
as well as the development of multiple
programming languages maybe that are
representing a certain equation and
giving a lot of continuity
with the terms and the tools and the
points of reference within the book and
all of that is being threaded together
really by the active inference ontology
which has been in development since
really the initial days of the lab so
it's just awesome to see this new
knowledge artifact come on to the scene
a new modification in the niche
new textbook has entered the chat
and then be able to organize rapidly and
have a bunch of participants get
involved um what would anybody else like
to add about the textbook group
it's different than a paper
it has similarities with papers
but it is very different
so it's been a great experience
anything else though yeah alex
yeah i think it was also interesting
interesting experience how
subgroup for math learning was
organized
like by initiative of participants and
how we started to work on like
additional direction and provide more
energy and more efforts to structure
math side of the book
what yeah and this is
our first
attempt in such activity and
as i see it it has a lot of
opportunities for learners
and
really helps to
acknowledge all the concepts and all the
idea
of active inference
great
okay
um moving on to another educational
effort the internal systems thinking
ongoing activity
alex would you like to describe a little
bit here or on
i can say that from the beginning it was
part of our strategy to use system
thinking intelligent to organize work on
projects and
it is
like
a requirement for lab participants to
have an understanding of concepts of
system thinking
so having this educational activity for
people who are willing to learn it and
later to to take part in different roles
in
labs project
for for us
it's
like a basement for all we're doing and
we are also
learning by doing this education
and hopefully
new version of textbook and the program
which we're using here will help us
to be
more and more efficient in all projects
that we are doing
any other comments here
yeah we launched this
type of activity to have a
common language for
all
of the participants
and this course is providing such
language
and
it it is uh
one of the uh
one of the
such
activity and i hope we will continue
with
different
different types of
educational
formats great
okay
continuing on
we have also in education
there was a lot of development in q2
with our knowledge engineering
and knowledge corpus project
blue would you like to provide initial
summary
sure so i think we've described this
project before but just briefly we are
taking the open source papers from
pubmed that have active inference or
free energy principle as keywords
and we've
put all of these papers into a database
and with all of the authors and all of
the metadata
and and
we are
then scraping them and parsing out the
text
for
keywords from our ontology and this is
shown here in the heat map
this top right figure
it shows all the different like
ontology words and how they they cluster
per paper so we've looked at keyword
clustering and
authorship like this is first author
papers by year
so
we can kind of see trends in active
inference but but this will serve as
then
a way for our ontology to access
the um original data so if you're
looking for words in the ontology
something you don't understand like
markov blanket or something like this
you can actually find go straight to the
horse's mouth so to speak and find
papers that reference this maybe that
reference it a lot
and so we're intending to publish this
and then really we want to build
a
reflexive system and invite people to
upload their own papers
and we're also starting to get papers
from archive now um and then we also
will invite people to upload papers that
maybe are not open access that they want
to have catalogued in our database so
it's really a fun interesting data
sciencey project that i've enjoyed
working on with daniel and our colleague
rj so yeah
yeah just just to um
show that that heat map again where the
columns are the terms and the frequency
of their use
and the rows are different clusters of
papers so this is like topic modeling
it's identifying clusters of terms that
have a similar coexpression pattern
and so it was really fun to apply this
kind of uh heat mapping and clustering
and some statistical techniques because
both blue and i have worked with gene
expression analyses where the rows would
be like the genes in the genome and the
columns would be
how much different genes are expressed
in different samples and so the ontology
is kind of like the genome
because there's one copy of every term
it's like a dictionary
and then
some terms are used a lot or little or
not at all in any given library in any
given sample of text
and so it's showing how the expression
of the ontology and of terms
relates to this in our case
a reference genome of not just the whole
language dictionary but specifically the
active ontology as a versioning and
developing artifact so then
rhetorical and conceptual relationships
can be drawn
in principle
amongst ontology terms
like here's the relationship between
markov blanket and frist and blanket or
whatever other terms are being linked
and also that can be integrated with
empirical results from the literature
and also translated across different
language to facilitate all kinds of
education
and research assistance so this will be
really fun and as blue mentioned we're
hoping to release the written paper
and the tooling around this kind of a
pipeline which includes
people being able to submit papers in
annotate and update the information and
then also have a rendering output
and
hopefully we'll provide an update on
that soon but it was a fun quarter for
this project
any other comments on knowledge
engineering
okay
all right in
education we also had a great
quarter of live streams
so the two main series of live streams
that we
had this quarter
we had some guest streams and we had our
regular paper discussion live streams so
in the guest streams we had
uh marco facton adam saffron shannon
proch anna lemke
maxwell ramstead and dalton
saxdevel as well as just yesterday with
professor steven grossberg so a lot of
awesome guest streams
one off
presentations and discussions on active
inference research really like core and
cutting edge work as well as work that
might not explicitly mention active
inference but is super consistent and of
general interest like with professor
lemke it was a great discussion on
dopamine
and in the paper live streams we've had
paper 41 42 43 44 45 and 46
working our way through the 40s
41 was on extended active inference 42
was on robotic navigation and the slam
simultaneous localization and mapping
43 was a theoretical and experimental
review related to predictive coding and
actin it was a mathematical review paper
was therapeutic alliance as active
inference the role of therapeutic touch
and their ian tennant
was really instrumental in coordinating
those discussions and preparing
as was sid in 42.
in 45 we talked about free energy
principle made simpler but not too
simple where
carl fristen and thomas parr
joined for those discussions
and provided some
great insights into this paper and
we had a very cheerful time and there
was a lot of surprises
and a lot of bayesian surprise too and
no surprise and amazing surprise are not
the same thing
as we've been discussing in the textbook
and then in the last two weeks we've
just completed
live stream number 46 on active models
do not contradict folk psychology which
was great
brought in some new people into live
streaming had some
conversations of broad interest related
to folk psychology and just
the way that the academic
the lived
and the day-to-day
perspectives on cognitive science and
experience
all come together and
even uncovered some of the
adjacencies there that go into
philosophical and even theological
angles so
awesome live streams by everyone who had
joined
and
yeah
a lot of learning happening
within these streams
any other
comments or
things that people want to know
particularly fun stream that they
watched or joined
i had so much fun in 45.1
like where i was deferred to as like the
expert on the paper
that's really funny like like uh like
carl was like well well blue how what do
you think
okay
um that was that was really like amusing
and cute
yeah it was really a memorable
experience was um beginning 45.1 i think
and when we hit start streaming blue and
i were the only people in the chat
and we didn't
have confirmation that anyone else would
join
so we just
trusted the plan
and had authors join quickly and so just
was like
it was very rapid um reduction of
uncertainty and yes as tradition
dictates
the authors um
passing to us
and it's that kind of like participatory
engagement
where
even though
they wrote the paper
the expertise and the perspectives are
still very distributed and hopefully
it's striking a new
and uh
productive and also value aligned way
to talk about research
and to continue to develop research
after artifacts are published in advance
of other artifacts and
just
hope that we can continue to integrate
in these discussions as like the tip of
the iceberg
the best of all worlds
in terms of
having the rigor and the clarity and the
conciseness where and as we need it and
also holding space
for
everything from basic questions things
that might not initially seem related
everything in between so
any other comments on
live streams
all right um we didn't talk about this
in the last quarterly lab meeting
but this was a paper
from
march 1st 2022.
the authors were myself uh sean
applicate swanson arghan chaudhary rj
corday
shadee l domiti
avel aka serval
blue here
yvonne here
sid said code
uh ahmet singh medemith
jakob here
caleb tuttle and alex here so a bunch of
us and a bunch of other colleagues
we had
a great time working on this paper
and what we did was we evaluated web 3
and blockchain technology in
relationship to the emerging area of
decentralized science dci
we also explored some opportunities for
where active inference could interface
with dsi
in theory and in practice as well
and that highlighted some important
conversations
around desai
in its technological aspects what kind
of technology is composing or moving the
frontier of desai in 2022
and then more in principle what does it
mean for science to be decentralized
decentralized in what way
wasn't it always decentralized what
kinds of failure modes across multiple
scales
do decentralized systems present them
themselves with
so we in the first part of this paper
evaluated
decentralized science desai
and just covered some historical threads
that a lot of the co-authors just shared
amazing views on
we then
presented an active entity ontology for
science or eos
and presented it in coda tables but
we'll talk more about how we're
continuing to develop it
it is a composable and versionable
modeling system
that uses the active inference entity
partition with the blankets
and the same ontology terms that we
would use to describe particular
entities partitioned states like
affordances and policies and so on
and
separated types of entities into two
main types active entities which are
like adaptive active entities they're
able to undertake actions and modify
their niche
and informational entities
which are also partitioned entities but
do not engage in action selection so
like a pdf of a paper it's an
informational entity it's in the
epistemic niche but it's not taking
actions whereas active entities ranging
from humans or
programs as well as organizational
institutional type entities across
multiple scales
are engaging in communication and
actions around their epistemic niche
that is providing a
foundation and a grounding
for continued discussions that we're
having about how to bring integrity and
continuity amongst natural language
representations visual representations
and simulation type representations of
complex digital and cyber physical
systems
so would any of the other authors like
to
share like
anything that i missed or one part about
this paper that they found
useful or interesting to work on
so i'll share i i thought um this paper
was interesting because there was a or
or there is
quite quite a bit of tension between
decentralization in terms of
like distributed effort and labor and
also like dsi as
like a market based
um entity or or idea
and so resolving these two um
these two things or like the tension and
juxtaposition of of what is design is it
just the distribution of knowledge and
um
resources or is it more based on based
on markets and blockchain
i think that that was one of the key
insights brought upon by this paper
yes
and
hopefully we'll have more spaces and
times to explore and draw out some of
these threads maybe even a guest stream
with these authors
but
what is today known as web3 and
blockchain is
developing and growing out of and beyond
financial technology
and
perhaps there's a sense or an argument
in which financial technology are some
of the sinews and connective tissues by
which science occurs
like
value and
financial
actions occur in scientific and
epistemic ecosystems
but
is that the common denominator will we
be
financial reductionists with respect to
how we model for example motivation
and all these types of
cognitive features
in epistemic ecosystems
at the same time
there's many features
of
blockchain systems that make them a
natural fit for scientific information
so
it's an ongoing discussion and and
hopefully those with
interest in desai or in these kinds of
technologies overall we'll just stay
tuned and get involved because we're
just beginning this avenue of
development okay any comments here or
we'll continue
okay
uh next we'll talk about some research
and applications we'll talk about the
active block funds project
so jacob do you want to provide a little
summary of active block prints
um so active block friends is
um
work in progress python package that
connects
um
the recent
new library
for model for modeling uh agents with
active inference
uh called prime dp and another library
called cat cat which
is used a lot in economic and complex
system simulations
so active bug for instance right now
the combination of the
active imprint agents are
um
are modeled within within cad cad
um and
currently currently it's still very much
work in progress the
the overall structure of the
of the package is
still being developed and we're working
on um
kind of polishing polishing the the the
implementation of prime dp and tailoring
it more towards the
uh cad cat style of development and also
working on
problems uh how to
increase the complexity of the of the
models with like multi-agent modeling or
different constraints
thanks
so pi mdp just for context is a python
package
that has recently been developed
and it provides a very
simplified foothold for python
programming to be implementing the kinds
of markov decision processes that's mdp
that are used in some formulations of
active inference
and so
it's an incredibly important package to
use
and also there are some other features
that are requisite to use for systems
engineering
for
the kinds of generative models and
generative processes that we might want
to implement
in
real applied active inference settings
for example parameter sweeping
architectures and being able to specify
execution orders and have some
reproducibility around certain kinds of
simulations various features that the
cad cad framework provides for so as
jakob mentioned at the very beginning
the multi-agent case is quite
interesting like
does each entity
perceive and then act and then we
cascade through them in the same order
different order
or is there some other
structures and execution orders how does
that influence
active inference simulations
with metamouth i've been continuing to
work on the next generation of the
active infra ant
colony simulation so i hope to share
more specifics when we have it but this
is a continuation of the work that was
done in 2021 with several
colleagues we're working on various
other
aspects of the package
and this last one here connecting to
ethereum or other web 3 ecosystems
so just to kind of hinge on that and
look into the next slide
for the active block prints project
there was a ecosystem support program
grant available from the ethereum
foundation
and we proposed in a grants application
about a month ago to expand our current
simulations
into multi-agent setting
in order to explore cognition and
behavior underlying
desai and d5 projects
the grant was not funded so the foraging
continues
but it was a great learning experience
and it um
helped us
sharpen
and elaborate on everything from the
substance of the package itself to the
communications around it and have
preliminary discussions on how do we
balance in a distributed team
retroactive funding proactive funding
and so on
specifically we were proposing to
develop multi-agents some case studies
and digital twins that already exist in
the ethereum ecosystem
porting those over into
an active inference
framework and helping
characterize scenarios and phenomena
that had previously been only approached
from a top down essentially macro
economic
type of simulation like if the interest
rate is this amount and this is the
other parameter on this macro then
here's how the system will evolve
trying to complement that with a
bottom-up
cognitive entity decision making
framework that could be used in a lot of
interesting ways
specifically we were interested about
the possibility and still are
of performing these kinds of cognitive
audits which is a terminology used in
various artificial intelligence fields
but a cognitive audit could provide
insights into if potentially there was
some smart contract or
series of cyber physical relationships
where from a computer security or
network security perspective it was
airtight
however
in the cognitive niche
perhaps there were destabilizing
forces or dynamics
and although it wouldn't have been part
of our initial work we hope to
eventually include cognitive features
even like for example narrative and
sentiment such that different kinds of
information natural language reading and
writing all these kinds of features of
real cognitive systems could be
integrated into these increasingly
actionable
and coherent
digital twin site type simulations so if
anybody is interested to
get more involved in active block prints
whether they have familiarity with
python cad cad academ
all or none of the above
everybody is welcome to get involved and
also if anyone has insights into
how
such a project might receive some
funding we're also open to those
thoughts
anything else on the gr application
okay
we on the engagement and outreach
frontier
continued
connecting with
new and returning participants on
different platforms
we saw growth across our discord
twitter
podcast channel
and youtube channel
so
it was a good
quarter of activity on these fronts and
of course always feel free to share our
public information or invite other
people who you think might want to get
involved but we continue with the work
and these are our active states
in the epistemic niche
any funny tweets
any memorable emojis
okay
and then
um closing out the project updates
on the
staying on the engagement and outreach
theme
we have some
uh directions
that are coalescing relating to the
engagement and outreach at active lab
so
first we are developing an internship
program
that will share more details on but will
provide a much more scaffolded project
specific way for individuals who want to
on-ramp into the lab or to step up their
activity
and learn by doing that way
we've written some letters of support
for applications at university programs
with
more information should these
applications of our colleagues be
accepted
we believe that this kind of a
institution to institution partnership
is going to be uh
there's going to be a lot of affordances
for win-win opportunities
with different institutions reaching out
to octave lab and having a relationship
where we can each contribute
what we can do and
be part of some
joint action some generalized synchrony
and also
especially through the
relentless work
of dave douglas
we've been improving our subtitles
and language translation
progress which we'll talk more about but
language translation includes math so
just at this first pass
it's raising attention to
the way in which
whether it's audio
content or textual content or morphing
in between with speech to text and
text-to-speech
annotation and translation
is the basis of rigorous scholarship as
well as accessible information
so making sure that whatever the initial
artifact is
that it can be consumed and enjoyed in
the sensory modality that's most
accessible to a given person
and translated into the natural language
computer languages and so on that are
most familiar to somebody
again also helps with accessibility and
rigor so just like we looked at with the
textbook group with the math as a
language truly being translated into
natural language using ontology terms
that will facilitate translations
amongst different languages
that will just make sure that from the
first step to the 99th step
of learning and applying active
inference that it's really a coherent
and a comprehensive experience
so
really awesome
directions and if anyone sees
opportunities
to
join in engagement and outreach with us
of course
please feel free to just contact us
any other comments on project updates
on this section
okay
so the next section of this lab meeting
will be about the next steps at the
project scale
starting with the theme of education
as mentioned we are completing the first
cohort first part of the active textbook
group
after cohort 1 part 1 we'll finish up
through chapter 5 in the end of july
we're going to take august off and then
we are going to pick back up with
two parallel cohorts there's going to be
cohort one
continuing on with part two of the
textbook so that those first cohort can
finish the textbook at least a first
pass on it during 2022
we will then also begin cohort two of
part one so these will be a totally new
batch of people who are coming in and
starting on chapter one
and people from cohort one who want to
just take a second pass um
i think we all do in a sense whether we
take the plunge to be in cohort two or
not is a different question but
all these materials are the kinds of
things that we can just get many coats
of paint on and learn and read again and
again
we're really excited for this second
cohort
because we'll be incorporating a lot of
what we're learning from the first
cohort
into how we proceed with this second uh
cohort as well as with part two in the
first cohort
and
hopefully this is just the first few of
many many textbook group cohorts
because it provides a very accessible
on-ramp
into learning and applying active
inference the textbook is written with
that kind of learning and applying in
mind
and
hopefully these textbook groups
are providing a service that
makes that on-ramp even smoother and
more fun and with more image memes
and with more connecting the dots and
more exercises to test more
opportunities to ask questions
um
and i'll put the link in the youtube
chat for registering to participate in
an upcoming cohort does anyone else want
to add anything about
this
next steps on the textbook group
just that it's a great opportunity to
get involved if you want to learn more
about active inference or even if like
you're starting at ground zero we've had
some people come in with like no idea
about the math and
um yeah it's been i think really useful
to work with everyone from all levels to
kind of try to make this field more
accessible
awesome
okay
also on the
education theme
so as
suggested in some of the updates
we're learning a lot
from the textbook group
and other educational projects
that are occurring in the lab like the
active inference ontology development
and live streams
and
with education and research as our
mission we've always been interested in
developing
some active inference courses and
educational experiences
um
alex do you want to provide some updates
on how we'll be continuing here
yeah thanks
this activity on creating
online course is also as
many hours is uh
learning by doing for
our own for creating courses because we
understand that for different uh
audiences different courses need to be
created
and finally we should have like as
a bunch of different ones and this
introduction and introductory uh course
will be
an example of organizing the team
of different educational roles which you
understand needed to take part of
creating
a course which should be
quality have quality and have
accessibility and so on that's why
based on experience and the materials
and results of
textbook group
including and developing different types
of
cases and examples into online form
which can be supported
by
online platform which we'll be using
from systems management school
it will be the first step
to
broad set of educational materials for
any new people who will
starting to learn active inference and
we will
create courses and improve it
[Music]
improve set of courses to make it
accessible to as much people as possible
yes in the
long arc
of
education and even just active inference
education
this is a modified curio card yes i
right click saved it
and now
on the top of this pile of books is the
active inference textbook and it's just
reflecting like one more
epistemic niche modification
and it is
coming after
of course many papers and also other
kinds of educational materials that have
been prepared ranging from short form
workshops that have been held in
different locations to
blogs
and github repositories like famously a
barren millage
of just informative links
and those are all very important
educational formats
however
there is nothing like an active
inference course
and for a course to be
done right and versioned
in our
attentional situation
and with our conceptual focus on active
inference
it's quite a challenge but there's also
an amazing opportunity here
so
for those who would like to be learning
more about how to participate
this is
one way to be getting involved at some
stage with the team or
with the feedback on the initial course
or of course just as with the textbook
group the early cohorts who co-create in
this
participatory way so this is super
exciting and also we've had a lot of
great contributions from participants
from
dean jessica brock so many others who
have added and helped us
build um
a lot of like a
a garage of spare parts
and motifs and considerations
that
when we formalize the course team will
be able to be taken into account and
implemented
okay
um all right
on the education theme as well
let's talk about the
systems thinking
summer intensive
yvonne or alex wanna describe what will
be happening in august 22
yes uh in august we will launch
a branch activity of system thinking
course
and it will
unpack
the base concepts of the system one of
the base concepts
system thinking it's roles and
row based
descriptions
um
for four weeks
we will define
what the roles are
how we can use it to
have a
common meaning with
how we can see different things
in
a way to understand each other
yeah uh that's it
great alex on anything
okay
all right so
in educational activities
we are announcing some of the early
sketching around the internship program
which perhaps
by any other name would it smell so
sweet
it's really like
a learning by doing scaffolded
affordance
it is a
self-driven opportunity for individuals
of all ages larval stages
backgrounds etc
to engage in personal learning and
development that will be related in a
large part
to project-based contributions to active
lab so it'll be
win-win
you'll be learning by doing and
contributing to the lab as well and
helping projects develop
the
duration and time commitment
we're figuring out some details but
we'll be able to make it work for people
who want to be involved we'll find a way
to make it happen
for those who engage in this
type of internship
beyond
the
priceless value
of learning and development
and
being on the trajectory of acting
inferring serving
the lab can also offer
everything from letters of
recommendation and guidance and
mentorship
as well as increased access to the
digital research architecture of the lab
and we also hope to
provide more affordances as we
gain resources and organizational
complexity
and
these uh internships will be centered
around a target project
although there will also be
curriculum of the internship that is not
related to a project like related to
watching live streams or engaging in the
textbook group cohorts but a lot of the
contribution will be focused on a
project that will be carried out in a
structured way so it'll provide again
great opportunities for people who have
skills that they would like to apply
skills they'd like to learn
for now the best way to learn more about
this internship
whether you're interested or whether you
know of somebody who might like to
maybe get involved
would be to contact us at
activeinference gmail.com
and or to register for the systems
thinking summer intensive because these
projects will have role-based approaches
to participating so the summer intensive
is a couple weeks long a couple of hours
per week and it will provide a nice
warm-up for getting involved in a
role-based internship
program okay any other thoughts here
okay
also in our next steps
we are
expanding and scaling the active
inference journal
so this is again
work with several participants
and especially dave
we've been
preparing
a sequence of work and practices and
roles
so that for our past catalog of live
streams and other presentations
and going forward
we will be able to
have a effective and automatable and
also just documentable and reproducible
approach
for
preparing the transcript of a speech
event
into
an edited curated format that can then
be rendered into
on one hand a prose based format which
can be published for indexing citing and
searching and on the other hand into a
subtitle format that will facilitate
accessibility of the videos and also
that can all be translated across
different languages so
it'll be really exciting to
really nail down
our practices
and ways of working
such that
within
several days potentially after a live
stream occurring
we could publish a very high quality
annotated
artifact
that could leverage the impact of a lot
of these very important conversations
that are happening
and
anything else to add on the journal
all right
we will
announce here
that we are having a second applied
active inference symposium
on the theme of robotics
it will be held on july 31st 2022
from four to eight
and 16 to 20 utc
so all the dates and times are utc it's
a four hour first interval 12 hour break
or sorry
eight hour break
and then um another four hour interval
stay tuned on social media and our
newsletter
for more information including
presenters
we've been having a
great time collaborating with
co-organizers matt brown and mark miller
as well as some of us on this call
and
in the last year or two there have just
been many
important introductory works
bridging
active inference
and robotics
so for example here's an image from how
active inference could revolutionize
robotics of decosta at all recently
as well as the paper that we discussed
of catal at all in april in livestream
42 on the simultaneous localization and
mapping so we
hope to
hold this symposium
where there will be
presentations
and roundtable type discussions that are
live streamed as well as recorded and
re-watchable
and also with transcripts that will be
published as proceedings
to highlight some issues
and opportunities in
this
increasingly important area of active
inference and robotics so we hope to be
drawing on many perspectives
those who are coming at
the active robotics intersection from
the perspective of
researchers
industries uh involved in robotics or
active inference those with curiosity
those with philosophical interests in
these topics ethics and the social
implications there's going to be a lot
of great discussions around this
symposium so just stay tuned and we'll
have more information coming out soon
any other
comments on the symposium or any other
next steps for projects
okay
so
one new thing
special announcement time
as of
june 2022 this month
we are formalizing a transformation at
the organizational scale
from the active inference lab into the
active inference institute
so
use those emojis
but this has been a really exciting
development
and we like to just share a little bit
about it now
we've been working with freed frank
in a pro bono law firm capacity
and they've been helping guide this
developmental process
we're initiating
some
enterprise architecture development
such as
updating and improving our governance
structure
obtaining funding and hiring for
research and educational roles and
identification of focal projects as
affordances for onboarding
more generally
this
move in generative model or markov
blanket from the active lab to the
active inference institute
helps us
clarify and continue on with our
strategy
around education and research and
the time has come for something
different and bigger and so we hope that
the aii
organization will be able to
represent that and scaffold that and
provide those services to our niche in
the best possible way
i guess there's a ton to
share and ask and in the coming few
slides we'll talk a little bit about
strategy but
what do people want to add here about
this just for now
i want to say that
these changes on organizational scale
from one hand reflects
the growing number of services that we
are providing to to the niche
and from the other hand
is an answer for growing complexity of
activities and
i believe that after we analyzing
immigration projects
before beginning of next semester
we will be really ready for
scaling of our activities
and to include more people
to participate and having that
scale to
the opportunity to grow and having as a
ability to to have it is ability to grow
within
new
[Music]
skills and
have a
possible groups departments and
different types of projects and support
different types of collaborations
thanks anyone else want to
add before we talk about strategy a
little bit
we just want to
oh yeah blue please
i just wanted to add that um
i don't know it's a
a
really involved process
becoming a 501 3c and thinking about
governance structure and
how that fits into our strategy and
balancing
the things we have to do like
obligational
commitments in order to
further the success of the active
inference institute and also like the
fun things that we like to do like
research and papers and textbook groups
and and things like that so so striking
a balance has been like interesting
challenging
and hopefully it'll be rewarding
yes
it's uh
only 18 months ago
when we
began the lab in in the beginning of
and we very immediately afterwards began
the process of formalizing as a
non-profit we did end up doing that in a
california nonprofit
and
that was a um
good step that helped us get a taste of
the kinds of enterprise architecture
that we would
ultimately need
and now we're ready to face those
challenges and opportunities really
directly with this new approach so it's
super exciting and we just wanted to
include it in this lab meeting as recent
developments
and more will be coming in the coming
months
in july of 22 we'll take kind of a
summer break there won't be any live
stream paper discussions
and during that time we'll be
having a lot of migrations and
updates so just stay tuned
for things to be
updating as they do
in the act institute
let's talk a little bit about strategy
so
here we'll present a update on our
strategy document
that um as
we update this at the quarterly scale
we'll be helping to guide
some of the next development steps in
the active institute
so
active inference institute aii or you
can use emojis with just an a and then
the 2i emoji
is on the path of open-endedness our
strategy considers learning and applying
active inference for changes in the
niche over multiple nested scales
through time we increase the degree of
hierarchical organization complexity to
overcome competing interactions and
frustrated states
we engage in policy selection reducing
our uncertainty about realizing our
expectations and preferences for
epistemic values as a non-profit
organization
at the same time
to ensure institute development we need
to secure pragmatic financial
sustainability with enabling activities
and the three scales
that the aii is modifying and
interacting with
are
first the participant as an agent
the human participant
the institute provides affordances and
updates participants generative models
via providing them a modified niche
with the institute as an agent
this level
is where we can engage in institute
level policy selection and then and
evolve a shared generative model that
goes beyond any one participant
and then lastly we are modifying and
interacting with our communities
and peer organizations in our epistemic
niche
where we provide services and
opportunities and engage in
collaborations with community so
any overall thoughts on this
okay
to
our
first
area of focus
thank you blue
our first area of focus is education
at the participant scale
we approach the participants active
inference mastery as the system of
interest
to reflect the plurality of individual
priors
expertise levels and preferences
we develop different educational formats
such as workshops discussion groups
online courses project-based learning
internships and more
and our preference is to have up to a
hundred participants involved in
education by the end of 2022
at the institute scale we're learning
state-of-the-art ways of working and
practices across functional domains to
build and strengthen our organizational
capacities
and at the community scale we work on
education and reducing research debt for
broad communities
we develop public video and audio
content
that spreads and we prefer to reach out
to
many dozens of thousands of people with
the information that we create
any other like thoughts or ideas on
education
i think it's exciting to explore
what
the future
and the presence of education are
we've seen only the early days of online
education
even though there's been many effective
or less effective approaches tried
there's so much
to
develop around how we educate especially
for the active inference area
two related to research
at the participant scale we provide
affordances to scaffold and launch
research and development projects by
participants
projects can be driven by participants
inside or outside of our organization
and the institute will provide relevant
support
we expect to see dozens of research
outcomes in the coming months and years
ranging from papers workshop and
conference presentations
and from the basic to the applied
at the institute scale
as an organization we rearrange we
catalyze and participate in active
inference research projects
with long-term impact or public goods
features like ontology development
knowledge engineering and also events
such as symposiums and conferences
at the community scale
we recognize and seek to carry out apply
and improve upon
research practices from open science
desai
beyond
so
to be caught up
education d-school
and then to go beyond
and create novelty
and discover on the frontier research
like desai
those are the two
key
and first focuses of the active
institute
the third is outreach and engagement
so at the participant scale
we think of participants as ambassadors
of the institute so we welcome and
support their initiatives to share a
voice about active inference in various
situations and communities
at the institute scale we aim to set up
partnerships with other organizations
from academia industry and beyond
this supports high quality
science communication education and
collaborations around research topics
such as active inference
and at the community scale
we acknowledge the diversity of people's
initial conditions
for example their familiarity with
different languages
science philosophy computation
everything
we develop projects of uh like the
active inference online journal and
create popular science content for
different social media
and we hope to provide
a
portfolio of outreach and engagement
opportunities again to meet
those who are interested
where and how
they are
any other thoughts or ideas on this
so just a thought on the research
strategy
for people that might have projects that
didn't start in the active inference lab
or projects that they want to start and
haven't yet started
we don't necessarily
start projects sometimes projects come
to us so if you're looking for a network
of people or maybe weekly meetings with
feedback or
something else to scaffold your project
we can provide access to a big community
of active inference researchers and like
would welcome projects that have already
taken off so if you have a project that
you want to bring into the lab that is
open science that's i think one of the
key things for for the lab um we would
just welcome that opportunity to work
with anyone who wants to do an active
inference based project
thanks blue and yeah hopefully we can
have more
exemplars and
clear
lanes
and the uh mystery lanes for those that
don't even yet exist but there's a
continuum of ways to participate in
project-based learning
ranging from coming to an act institute
scaffolded project where we will help
with the rhythm the infrastructure the
role assignment and everything it's kind
of like a show up and enter the game
type project
there also might be projects that are
totally off the radar of act institute
it's just
you are participating
in a project or not but you're
connecting with participants in in the
organization and you find a latent
interest and you collaborate that way
with your own
font
formal documents ontologies narrative
and tools
or something in the middle where you
have a project that's at a stage where
you're ready to get feedback from the
active inference community or just from
any interested people
maybe there's opportunities to
collaborate or maybe you're looking for
just some help on tweaking it and
fine-tuning it as you prepare for
example to submit a paper or develop the
next version of something so there's so
many ways to do
research and education
that we will just have clarity around
where
is
the projects that the institute is
scaffolding and moving the needle on
and those are the kind of massively
collaborative projects where people who
want to be involved can kind of get
involved and check back in and out
all the way to projects that are
self-driven and you're
seeing the lab as again a niche that is
modified for you to support those kinds
of research efforts like one exciting
opportunity there
is for individuals who would like to be
writing or building applications
that use active inference to gain some
familiarity with the ontology could go a
long way and somebody could just hang
out in the relevant meetings or read the
relevant documents and publications
and then that is like a way to close the
feedback loop and to use these services
that are being provided in the niche
like the ontology and so reduce research
debt by promoting coherent and
comprehensive use of active inference
terms and concepts and so there's many
ways to uh learn and research and apply
aligned with this
overview
strategy work in progress we're
presenting here
and lastly four methods
at the participant scale we educate
participants so they grow their
expertise level in different disciplines
as disciplinary expertise entails
competency in various practices and
tools
we take a holistic approach to
participant professional development
at the institute scale
communication and organizational design
our
are our fundamental effort
we apply active inference systems
thinking and other first principles
approaches to the institute operations
and at the community scale
we share and promote methods
we use throughout the community to
increase the quality and efficiency of
collaborations and we're also open to
recommendations for new methods and
strategies to consider
so
methods is a little bit of the how
just as if it were a scientific paper
and the what is education research
outreach and engagement
so
this lab meeting has consisted a little
bit of a
introduction section again sticking with
this scientific paper metaphor an
introduction
of updates
maybe also those are our results
some discussions and next steps
and
now
with this one new thing
we
are also
pointing the way in which
we are heading
during this ongoing transformation
into the active inference institute
and so
it's a really
exciting time
for
those who are
involved
and paying attention
we
expect and prefer
and
there's many
opportunities
to be getting more involved
in any number of ways
ranging from educational opportunities
to joining
the kinds of projects where you can be
engaged in
research
education development
application
many opportunities there
and
it's just the beginning for the
institute so
much more
will be happening
as time flies
what else would people like to
address or
ask or bring up
in closing
i want to say that
results and plans what we are having
reflects our
[Music]
initiatives in a really long time scale
and we understand that
we can evaluate results like in one or
two decades and save it to his first
initial small steps
were like
a big beginning on something big
and
as for strategy
and all that we have now is uh like
applications of approaches that we
choose in the beginning
and an example of strategy which is like
a process for us and uh that updates on
quarterly
quarterly based updates of the strategy
is important because it's provided way
to be adaptive and react on changes on
information we're getting in the process
of work
and also consideration
an institute and a strategy on at least
three scales of
that we are paying attention to and
planning changes for free scales is also
providing our
to us a lot of opportunities to
affect
different
aspects and
niches which are related
and that's why
being from one hand have a very long
time horizonte in our planning
and
at the same time
having but very flexible approach to
development
like with
cornerstones of first principles and
kind of a
evolutionary and
open-endedness approach
i believe will bring us very interesting
result but very interesting results at
the end
does anyone else want to add anything or
i'll make a note we can continue
discussing
so one one conversation that
um jacob and i and others were kind of
developing and and memeing out over the
quarter
was
like what if active inference only works
for like one or two time steps
and
as we consider deeper and deeper even
potentially two in the most extreme
versions of the meme
that the combinatorics of decision
making
in principle and or in practice
become
challenging to evaluate and compute
like the computational complexity grows
potentially extremely rapidly
considering even two moves deep so to
speak
we've seen several approaches to dealing
with this bull first is the continuous
time approximation of active inference
where there is no explicit time series
prediction of future time points there's
just like a taylor series approximation
based upon the generalized coordinates
of motion
other approaches we've seen are deep
active inference just rolling out that
prediction to deeper and deeper time
points anyway and then utilizing
heuristics and other algorithmic
approaches to
ameliorate that combo torque and we've
also seen
sophisticated
or hierarchical active inference
modeling where potentially at two or
more hierarchically nested scales of the
model
still only one or two time points or
only a few time points have to be
reflected so it'd be like to predict out
a hundred years
one could have a model with a temporal
depth of a hundred
or there could be
ten
time points each consisting of a decade
of 10 years
and so then
that could even be broken down
further
and so when alex was
talking about the way in which
there's an imperative to act
in an adaptive way
to not die and to live and to thrive and
to serve of course
but in many cases
there
are some challenges associated with
decision making we don't have the
ability to do a b testing or null
hypothesis or even just alternatives
over very long time scales over certain
levels of organization it might be
possible to do for an event that's rapid
or has a lot of individuals engaging
with it like a website a b testing might
work super well if 100 people are
looking at the website every day whereas
in organizational design there isn't
that much
of the same affordance
and
it speaks to the way in which our
multiple nested time scales of updating
hopefully provide clarity
so that we don't need to
be at the fast cycle
trying to predict out a hundred years
but with increasingly deep hierarchical
temporal models we might be able to act
adaptively in a multi-scale way so for
example in 2021
we were planning heavily on the quarter
time scale
introduced and assembled our scientific
advisory board which began operating in
and that was explicitly
after one year of operations
expanding our temporal horizon to the
one year time scale
now with the kind of
architectural updates that the act
institute is
providing and necessitating
we're thinking beyond
one year explicitly because questions
like
who can elect who
in the organization
they do play out over slower and slower
time scales
so
it's been
quite interesting even mostly
qualitatively
to be applying and transferring
what we're learning about multi-scale
decision making under uncertainty
from active inference which is
kind of what it's about
and apply it in the organizational
multi-scale context with the participant
and the projects and teams and the
institute scale and the community in the
niche scale
and so it's
already been very rewarding and we hope
effective
to
in a
principled way
bring our learnings and ideas about
organizational design and the vast
experience that so many participants do
bring
to the table on these issues
and coordinate around
carrying that out
in
the active inference ontology
in a sense
and using other pieces of the puzzle
that aren't
now or in the future even necessarily
part of the active inference ontology a
lot of those features we derive from
systems thinking
active inference isn't a project
management approach so there's gonna
have to be like more
than just the actin phontology to carry
out effective team management but
that's why we use multiple ways of
learning and researching
so it just
was very interesting how
some of the theoretical discussions that
we were having
literally about multi-scale planning in
multi-agent active simulations
and the kind of cognitive complexity
that needs to happen
on board the entity
what is their actual cognitive
complexity and awareness and affordances
versus how are we going to simulate it
how do we prevent the simulation from
like sneaking in extra information
how do we think about the role of stigma
g
and the modifications of the niche
and the cognitive offloading that could
happen in a multi-agent setting or in a
stigmatic context
that is in tight feedback
with the ways in which
we're also structuring
our own niche
and
a lot of that
really started to take an acceleration
point in the last several months
with
jakob's contribution of active block
friends and other individuals
contributions
and the seeds were planted in the work
even before octave lab existed with
viatgan at all 2020 on active inference
and
behavioral engineering systems thinking
and remote teams
so
it is a
long
game
but then long compared to what it's just
the game it is
and
multi-scale decision making with diverse
perspectives
over multiple spatial and temporal
scales are not like the end point or
some hot take
that is our starting point
for
planning as inference
and
i hope that all these threads can just
continue to develop over the time scales
that are appropriate and that we can
connect with the participants
who are interested
for those who see that
high quality
engagement and relationship building
and development
are
worthwhile
in terms of epistemic and pragmatic
value
and
sometimes that takes multiple years to
approach this exciting and developing
topic which is changing month by month
as our guest streams
just recently have been
highlighting so for those who feel
uncertain about
participating they feel some impulse to
get involved
now watching the live stream or
in the future
yes it's easy and absolutely valid to
feel
busy and like it's an affordance that's
not immediately preferable
and
i'm not saying drop everything and join
act institute
however again we hope that those who
have
paid attention to what we've shared
today and hopefully continue to share
and for those who resonate with the
approach that we're taking adaptively
resonate with the
strategic vision
and with the increasingly
clear and numerous affordances for
learning and researching
we hope to connect with you
individuals
and create services
that scale even beyond those who get
very active in the institute itself
and
so much more
is to come again it has been quite a
ride in the last um
six quarters and people can check our
quarterly roundtable meetings
which
are
slides are being modified up to the day
basically
and they're like
an honest representation of how things
are developing are uncertainties around
different
uh developments in the lab
we have nothing if not
honesty and clarity
and vision
so
there's no clean way to end it when one
has walked this deep down the plank but
i'll just
again you know appreciate everyone who's
helped in every
way to get us to this point from the
people who like
first were enthusiastic about the idea
of an active inference lab in the
beginning of 2021 and end of 2020
more than a year before the textbook
when it was and still to some extent is
uh
an assemblage of papers
with partially overlapping focus and
ontology uses and notation
and amidst that uncertainty
some people
did step up and they
acted and they inferred and they served
and now we're starting another chapter
and
the logo doesn't change
everything else is just continuing to
develop so
it's been a great
ride and thanks again to
everybody who even as just a listener
for now
has been involved in some way
in
really being a part of the embodiment
and the inaction of
active lab slash
act institute
so just
expect and prefer
epistemic and pragmatic value
and
may the gradient be with you
any last comments or we can end it there
okay
thank you fellows see you later
bye
you